All right, welcome back everybody.
Hopefully you got some coffee, had a
nice rest, you're feeling energized,
ready to hear a bit more about the
Darwin core data or data data package.
Just a second. Ah, there we go.
Now, there's a little bit of a change to
the session uh format this time. So last
time we went through all five speaker
presentations and had questions at the
end. Today at during this session we'll
after each presentation we'll have the
opportunity to to answer one or two
questions. We'll move to the next
speaker again move answer one or two
questions and then at the end there
should be some time for Q&A as well. And
without any further ado I would like to
welcome John McCor and he will give you
a nice overview and background to Darink
data packaging.
That looks good. I was so happy that we
had so much time for questions in the
previous session. You may not have been
in the previous session. What I'm going
to talk about now will cover a lot of
things that were questions. Uh so bear
with me on that. Another good thing was
we didn't have to go into a lot of gory
detail even from the questions. We're
gonna keep doing that here. So if you
came to find out how the internal
workings of the data package function,
I'll talk to you later. This isn't about
that.
Okay. So the topic was this. Kate
actually asked this same question in the
very first introduction last time and I
found that in order to have our broad
audience at this conference be on the
same page that that wasn't the starting
point. So I had to go backwards and ask
what is Darwin core? Darwin core is a
standard and it consists of documents
and it consists of vocabularies
vocabularies of all kinds. When I say
that I mean that there are uh classes,
there are concepts and there are
properties which are things about those
concepts like an event date where the
class is an event and the uh there are
sometimes recommendations for controlled
vocabularies for those properties which
are yet other kinds of vocabularies.
So Darwin treats with all of those
things.
I'm not pushing the right thing.
Okay. Uh so this is a bit of a uh
diagram showing what parts there are of
the Darwin core standard including some
things that are highlighted in yellow.
And I wanted to call these out because
these are things under consideration
right now that were not part of the
standard. So one thing that may not
recognize the complete significance of
is for the first time an attempt to make
a conceptual model a semantic layer for
Darwin core. So that's this document
called the conceptual model.
Uh, another part of the standard are the
terms that I talked about and in this
review we'll have new terms that are
needed in order to support the use cases
that are covered by the Darwin core data
package and we'll have changes proposed
to some existing terms to make things
more clear based on the semantics that
we're trying to implement here and uh
and the structure that we're we're
adding.
Hold on
there. So this slide adds a document, a
page, a web page that's part of the
Darwin core offerings. It's not actually
part of the standard. It's a quick
reference guide that tries to make as
simple as possible the understanding of
those terms that are part of Darwin
core. So it's a quick reference guide to
the classes and to the properties that
are used across Darwin core standard.
So
we've already talked in the previous
session about Darwin archives. Now what
are they? They're actually not part of
the standard but they use the standard
one document in the Darwin core standard
to implement things that we can all
understand because they follow a
specification. So Darwin core is a
packaging of data a format that uses
Darwin core terms and has schemas that
we use to share data
and that's governed the specification is
governed by a Darwin core text guide
which is part of the standard.
So what's the Darwin core data package?
We finally got to the original question.
It's the same thing. It's a way to
package the data for sharing but it uses
a different set of uh standards for how
the description of the structure is
described. So in the place of uh
oh sorry I won't go there and in there
is a proposed document for how to create
Darwin core data packages that is this
Darwin core data package guide. It's the
exact corlary of a Darwin core text
guide upon which Darwin core archives
are made. So if we're going to make
Darwin core data packages, we're going
to have to follow the Darwin core
conceptual or sorry the Darwin core data
package guide.
All of what we're talking about Darwin
core archives or Darwin core data
packages
follow in practice the Darwin core
conceptual model that I talked about.
Okay.
So, uh, Kate showed this but was timid
about going into the details. I'm going
to go through the details fast because
there are only a couple things to
highlight. They're the same they have
the same purpose archives and data
packages, but they have a difference.
And the differences are that there are
the there are limitations to the Darwin
core archive which says you can't go
more than one layer of connection deep
and the Darcore data package says that's
fine with me go as deep as you want. Um,
so if you think about these in terms of
our day-to-day technologies that we use,
you could think of Darwin core archives
as fitting very well in spreadsheets,
whereas Darwin core data packages would
be better suited to databases. So the
it's more of a flat model on a Darwin
core archive side and more of a
relationship a relational model on the
Darwin core data package side.
uh there are many things that are the
same.
There are no explicit
semantics in Darwin archives but it's
kind kind of understood from our
practice what the meaning is and the
data that we share that way. Uh both
Darwin core archives and dar core data
packages will rely on EML the ecological
markup language to share the metadata
about a data set. And then finally
underlying the data in both cases are
shared via CSV or tab delimited text
files. So that part's not different.
So what can a DRO data package do that a
Darwin core archive can't? First of all
uh an occurrence event is something
different from a collecting event. That
didn't used to be possible. you went
out, you collected something, you put it
in your uh your collection and the
moment of collection said that an
organism was there at that time. It's
not so descriptive of what happens in
paleo. You go and collect a rock, but
that's not the occurrence of the species
the spec the occurrence of the species
with millions of years ago. Perhaps a
different thing. So now we're able to
talk about that event separate from the
one that collected it. This is useful.
We've seen already in the various talks
earlier about how there was nesting
sometimes of material in case of the
herbarium sometimes in events in the
cases of surveys. The same is also true
of media which I'll show a little bit of
how that might work. Uh I think that
survey targets were already covered well
enough there. Here they're uh as opposed
to being written into Humbult Core with
a very few kinds of target scopes. Here
they're wide open. You define what's
important for your survey target,
whatever it might be.
Another thing that's uh different here
is you have the capacity to explicitly
define the roles that agents play
anywhere in your data.
Whereas in Darwin Core as it stands now,
they're sort of written in agent roles.
You can be an identifier, identify
things, you can record things in the
field, you can georreerence things, but
they're all predefined.
With agent roles, you can define any
role that any agent had.
Again, it's in your hands. You get to
decide that and say it. Uh we also cover
organism interactions in a more explicit
way than was possible with resource
relationships in Darwin archives. We
have ubiquitous ways to make
measurements or other assertions about
any part of the model whether it be
about people or events or material or
identification anything. We also have
you seen as you have seen added the
nuclei nucleotide analyses to this. And
another thing that is not evident at all
in any diagram that you see is the
capacity to declare a controlled
vocabulary that you are using. So not
only do we have terms that expect to be
populated with controlled vocabularies,
now we can say where your term is
defined.
So,
okay. So, I'm gonna ask the question,
why did we invent something new then?
Why didn't we just make Darwin core
archives work?
A simplic simplification. The first
thing is it would explode everybody's
current practice. your Darwin core
archives wouldn't work if we tried to
make it do what a Darwin core data
package needs to do in order to maintain
a community that has confidence in
standards and going forward. We need to
maintain that baseline and then add to
it. So the Darcore data packages adds to
it. The other thing that you might not
realize is that Darcore archives are
based on a technology we designed for
our community. There weren't
frictionless data packages when we did
this. So we made something up. It
doesn't work with what the rest of the
world is doing. So that's an advance
that I think helps us using frictions
data packages. So I want to do a quick
run through of a story which in a Darwin
core archive I would
uh typify as being a detective short
story. So Darwin core archive can make
you c allow you to capture a detective
short story. So here we have uh a bee
that was photographed by somebody. The
little icons for people say that the
person who did the media was in the
media table. The audiovisisual
extension. There are measurements or
facts that can be done by people. That's
an extension up there to the north with
the ruler. You can have the event where
someone captured it and you can say
things about uh what it was called using
an identification history. So that's a
detective short story. So now I'm going
to quickly add the capacity to do the
same thing and more with a Darwin core
data package. So here I would typify a
Darwin core data package not as the
short detective story but as an epic
novel or the capacity to have an epic
novel. So I see a bunch of bees in the
field and me I say okay I I know what
those are. I'm going to give them a
name. I've made an identification.
I'm also interested in a particular bee.
And the reason I'm interested in that
particular bee is because it went and it
landed on a flower. I want to capture
that because my what I'm doing here is
I'm making a survey that says uh what
are the bee populations? It's a
monitoring survey of bees and I'm
particularly interested in when they do
interesting things like land on flowers.
So, I've got a bee. I've got the flower.
I've got the name for the flower as
well. I'm not real good at flowers, so I
give it a provisional name. I even put a
vernacular name on that one. And but I
take a picture.
Sorry, I don't take a picture yet. Uh, I
capture that bee because I need to make
sure of what that bee's identity is.
And I take a leg off of it. And I take a
DNA extra DNA extract off of that. And I
do a DNA sequence. And I use the
sequence to identify the bee to make
sure it was identified in the field. It
was identified. There's another arrow to
the bee itself in the lab as a specimen
and another one to the sequence. Three
different identifications
uh which may or may not agree with each
other. So can there be more to that
story? The answer is yes. As you might
have guessed, we can make measurements
or assertions about anything. So that
adds this to the model.
Can there be more? Well, yeah. We can
have media. We can have media about just
about anything. So, that adds all of
these arrows to the model. And can we do
resources? Can we say where we what we
made our identifications based on? Sure,
we can do that. And so, we can uh add
biblioraphic resources connected to all
kinds of things. For example, where the
sequence was me mentioned. Okay. So, and
agents, I already mentioned them. We add
a whole bunch more arrows. Okay. So, you
can see why we call that the epic novel
instead of the detective short story.
This is what's possible. Now, do you
have to do all that? No, not at all. You
only need to use what you need to use
and you decide that, not me.
So, here's a version of the epic novel
with all the things that might be
interesting put into appendices or not
shared at all. And you can see here that
I've collapsed all those agent roles
into the little teeny agents inside of
the material table or the media table or
so on because those are hardcoded.
Not only can I say anything about any
agent role, I have some that we already
know are interesting and those are
hardcoded and those are kept from Darwin
core as we know it today.
So, who should care about all this?
Well, the data publishers. Apparently,
they care because they're worried this
is all really complex.
um and the researchers who have the same
problem but probably have even more
interest in making sure that the effort
they spent on their research is
faithfully captured and shared and then
the decision makers ought to care about
this and then the people who have to
really help all these are the data
aggregators. So that's not a new story.
So where are we? What's next? We're in
the middle of a public review of various
aspects of additions and changes to
Darwin Core to support the kind of thing
that I was just talking about. And so
here we are in October 21st and the
public review began in middle of
September and we'll go at least until
the middle of December. Could go longer
depending on how we do with reaching a
consensus in our community.
And the idea is that when they're done
with that, there will be a ratified
additions to the standard. So what
commitments are there to Darwin core
data package? Well, first and foremost,
there will be continued support for
Darwin core archives. Not just in that
they will be accepted, but there will
also be training. In addition, there
will be continued and augmented support
for Darwin core data packages because we
know where we're at in this community
and we need to create capacity.
Publishing platforms such as the JBIFF
integrated publishing toolkit and the
metadata metabarcoding data toolkit
already publish Darwin core data
packages
in testing but they they do they work uh
we're we have a data mapping guide which
helps you to decide you know what's the
process what I need to go through to get
my data into a Darwin core data package
the order of events because it's kind of
a natural order of events that you have
to follow uh We already have seen in the
the use case examples everybody had
their repository of an example data set
already mapped. So you can have access
to those and part of the standard will
be the Darwin core uh sorry this isn't
part of the standard this is something
we have in in
progress is a Darwin core data package
users guide which we expect to be an
immense effort community produced
providing recipes for how to do certain
kinds of things I have this problem
here's how I solve that problem that's
what that should be and when this is All
done. Supposing we have ratification,
then all schemas will go under the uh
the maintenance of the Darwin core
maintenance group. These are additions
to Darwin. It will be a Darwin core
maintenance group maintenance problem
from then on out. And our hope is that
beginning in 2026, we'll actually have
scheduled releases every quarter as
opposed to when John has time to do it.
So,
um this is just a quick list. So I don't
want to go through what each one of
those is to give you an idea of what's
out there already to play with. And all
of those are accessible via the link in
the lower right
which is about the a landing page
basically for the ongoing Darwin Corp
data package review.
So thank you.
We do have time for questions. Yes.
two says
there's one here. Here comes a a
microphone.
Hello, John. I like I like this a lot.
Sounds like extended specimen concept.
How is it similar or how is it
different?
It's the extended
specimen
almost entirely
uh
you know start over John be correct uh
the digital specimen effort we've gone
through the process of doing the mapping
and it was found that it was actually as
opposed to what others may have
perceived it was actually easier for
them than it would be for most of you to
make the mapping because the structures
that they designed were already very
much like this
confirmed. Yeah. So, uh this isn't a
replacement for it. This is something
that used
cases that we defined through across all
kinds of uh biodiversity, not just uh
material
and covers some of the same area there.
Probably
Valter wants a followup with that. He He
deserves a followup. Can you
mic?
So um the uh the data model for the the
distal specimens
uh which should uh should capture should
enable this to extended specimens. was
not uh not created in isolation. It
started a bit earlier than this work but
um it was developed in the same same
time frame. So there was a lot of
communication to align these these
concepts and I think the uh the open
data model and there's a presentation
about that tomorrow um is a bit of
subset of of this because it's
specifically for specimens and this this
also capture uh other events. Mhm.
Thanks, Walter. Nikki's got her hand up.
That was time. Sorry. Later.
>> Thank you.
>> Thank you very much, John. I'd like to
welcome our next speaker to this speaker
to the stage, Anon Gch. He's going to
talk to you a little bit about ABCD and
how that fits into the data package
realm.
Yeah, many thanks and also uh many
thanks for the opportunity to present
here a little bit about ABCD
and uh I hear you're asking isn't this a
little bit off topic because after all
this is a Daring Cove data package
workshop but I hope that at the end of
my presentation you will agree that it's
not off topic and uh before
uh going to this I would like to take
you back a little into the history
uh of biodiversity data model. This is
30 years ago uh where this very
community
put their heads together, scratched
their heads and were working on data
models for observational and specimen
data. And one very prominent example is
the work I've mentioned here by Walter
Bansson who who created with his team a
comprehensive reference model for
biological collections and surveys. And
this was if you look at the diagram it
was very much a relational model
describing the relevant classes. So we
would need as a community
um attribute definitions and uh
essential uh vocabularies we would need
and most importantly the relations
between our essential data classes
and those models mainly were mainly used
um for implementing local databases in
isolation more or less. It was rather
not intended to create data structures
for creating international networks and
for transferring data from A to B. Uh
and that was actually a pity because the
the models were quite elaborated and
very very uh well designed.
But nevertheless, the community started
to create pilots for networking data,
not using those complex data models, but
much simplified data models. Uh, one of
those pilots was the species analyst
networks, which many of you probably
still know that was based on the set
3950 standards, a standard. It was a
protocol mainly used in the uh library
community.
And another network early network was
the European natural history specimen
information network based in the EU and
based on HTTP mainly used for transfer
specimen information.
So that one used XML for encoding
responses based on a common uh document
type definition. It had had basic
classes, hierarchies and repeatable
elements. Um, I have to admit it had
limited scientific use because only a
few data sources could be connected. I
think like six or seven data sources.
But what came out of this project
actually was was the um the uh um I
don't know agreement that XML would be
the right way to go forward because it
had the right balance between
comprehensibility of the model and also
expressivity
and that was then actually the basis for
creating the uh Tedwick uh data standard
access to bi biological collection.
ction data ABCD which aimed at
harmonizing collection data across
networks. It was developed between 2001
and 2006 by an international global team
of experts and the major properties of
this model were that it was
comprehensive. Um I don't tell you how
many elements it has. It has many
hundreds. Is it is highly hierarchical
losing a little bit of the relational
exclusivity of the early models. It has
implemented a concept for variable
optimization which I will not talk about
because it was a mistake to do this.
only a few controlled vocabularies uh
and extension slots used for special
interest networks such as the global uh
genome biodiversity network and it had
uh the capabilities for capture
structured annotations.
The version history is
a mess.
we have some major versions and between
those major versions
strange things happened. There were if
you look at the uh version 206 C that's
a famous missing version. I don't know
why it's missing and where it is but
it's the missing version 5 minutes I
know um and there are other branches and
all kinds of versions created in in the
context of projects but the major
versions are ABCD 2.06 06. This is the
most widely used version as well as ABCD
2.1 which is used by the um bioank
community and now also ABCD 3.0 Z which
is uh which turned ABCD into a semantic
standard.
There's a lot of infrastructure software
infrastructure around ABCD. Some
components
which are used are the ABCD provider
software. There are tools for harvesting
and indexing ABCD documents and there's
also the portal software and monitoring
components for special interest
networks.
So how it is used? There are presently
100 installations worldwide of ABCD
providers over over 10 special interest
networks. ABCD is integrated into the
GBIFF data corpus. It is heavily used uh
in the national context in Germany by a
structure called NFT for biodiversity
for exchange between data exchange
between components in the system and
there's also a bioase help desk which
helps providers to um map their data to
ABCD and deliver it for example to GIF
but also ABCD is used as a kind of
container for other community standards.
examples are uh the extension for
geocciences also the DNA extension for
ABCD and there's also an anthropological
extension which uses the ABCD schema
so what does this have to do with Daring
core data package
once more if you remember the early
models the relational model models and
now have a look at the Daring core data
package
modeling it looks very similar. Both are
really relational structures. So for us
it's really for the ABCD and bioase
community it's really
a relief to see that now the original
idea of relational data representation
and transmitting relational structures
over the internet
uh finally comes true. So what we would
like to do as a bioase ABCD initiative
is really to support this initiative for
example for example by contributing to
the development and maintenance of the
ding code data package standard and also
uh for developing templates for typical
usage scenarios.
We will however continue the bioase help
desk. So we will not let the bioase ABCD
providers alone
but we will extend the focus of this
help desk to structured uh highly
structured data complex data using the
DAC data package technology
and um I can now can't read more what
here on the slide um
yeah that's actually again that we want
to to integrate the Darving core data
package structures into our help desk uh
uh structures
and that's exactly what I wanted to say.
Thank you.
We're currently a little bit behind
schedule, so we have time for one
question and then um other questions
we'll need to follow up with Anton
after.
Does anybody have a question?
Shanton.
So our next speaker Sam Lupang was not
able to make it here to the conference
this week unfortunately but he did
provide a virtual presentation which we
will show here momentarily
uh giving you an overview and
introduction to the integration of disco
with uh with Darcore data package.
Hello everybody. Um I'm Sam Leang and
I'm really sorry I can't be with you
there in
but I'm so happy that I get this
opportunity to present uh how Disco's
open DS open dual specimen facilitates
data entropy interoperability with the
Dore data package.
So, Disco um Disco stands for
the distributed system for scientific
collections and our aim is to facilitate
and accelerate the digitization of
European specimen data.
Uh we want to do this by creating rich
and high quality fair findable
accessible interoperable and reusable
digital objects. We call those FDOS's in
the form of digital extended specimens.
And what is dual extended specimen? Um
that's on the right side where we kind
of start with the specimen itself the
the physical object. We then create our
first meta data record of it often in a
collection management system. And this
is where Disco wants to create kind of
create those bridge those extra step to
the extended specimen where we link the
specimen information with data from
other infrastructures uh such as DNA
infrastructures or texonomic
infrastructures. And where um together
with with our members and and machines
we want to can uh uh curate and extend
the information so that in the end we
can create valuable research products
which can be used by researchers uh to
combat the uh biodiversity crisis that
we're in at the moment.
So going back um how how can we then
structure all this specimen data and
this was where we uh kind of struggled a
bit in 2022. So there was no real
standard that we could reuse. So we're
wondering should we create something
ourselves or is there something that we
that we kind of can reuse. Um but you
always the risk if you're thinking about
creating new data standard is that
you're there's already a situation where
there are different standards that might
not all be specific for your use case.
You're thinking well it's you know we
need to create something better. You
create a new standard and now you have
more standards that kind of need to be
interruptable with each other and you
you actually end up with the messier
landscape than you started out with. So
we would rather not do this and this was
also around the time where where John
Courage and Tim Robertson gave a
presentation on their work for the GBF
unified model which actually which
actually covered and aligned quite well
with the challenges that we were having.
So we we kind of decided that rather
than figuring out ourselves which is
also kind of a long and painful process
creating a data standard
um we would rather reuse the work that
they had been doing with the community
and see if we can align ourselves with
with that part and then as opens being
specifically at the specimen data
um which actually what we did and we
moved this forward through public review
last year and it's it's now being used
in production. And um now with the
development of the D core conceptual
model, the the next steps after the the
GB unified model, um we wanted to check
if we are still aligning in that regard.
Um and
um after extensive discussions and and
review um a lot of the things that we um
that we move forward with OpenDS is
still in alignment with with how the
conceptual model works and we kind of
view opends as a kind of separate
specimen specific implementation of this
dark conceptual model.
So the D core conceptual model which you
can see here I can a bit of overview of
actually kind of structures the D core
terms into classes and points out the
relationships to to to each other. Um
and it kind of gives a blueprint of of
how you can structure your typical
biodiversity information workflow. And
and in in that regard we see the Darcore
data package is a kind of full reference
implementation of it. It implements all
these classes in a specific civilization
structure uh and highly um normalized
stabular data structure where CSV files
are used and OpenS is is quite different
in this regard. We we focus ourselves on
uh specific specimen classes. So we
don't implement all classes. We don't
implement any of the nuclide analysis or
nuclide sequence. We really focus at the
specimen and we then structure it in an
object-oriented
um document of a document oriented
approach uh using JavaScript object
notation. So the the the specimen itself
is one big uh object and all the
information regarding the specimen is in
there. So we kind of denormalize uh all
that information and and duplicate that
information in each each object. Why is
that? Because we expect a lot of
mutation on single specimen. So we're
not doing large build aggregations. No,
we're doing mutations on single spec uh
specimens and that ask for kind of
different approach, different
serialization of that that data.
Um yet what are the advantages of of of
aligning to this conceptual model? Well,
for us um I think the biggest is that we
we hope to get a kind of common data
language and maybe not only a data
language but also a human language in
the sense that if we are talking about a
specific term um if we say Dharma
habitat that we all know
what we all have the same concept in our
mind on what that means. So we have this
the same vocabulary in in that sense. Uh
which is really really powerful if we
can can align that. Um and then of
course we hope to leverage this work by
by by implementing it based on this this
hopefully new new Tedwick standard. We
hope to leverage all this work of this
community of experts which which is
quite amazing that we have this deadway
community where we can collaboratively
put our effort into developing this
model uh and give feedback on it and uh
we ourselves can hopefully give a bit
back in in through our experience with
the model and see if we can work
together on continuously improving it.
And the other part is that we hope to
get a kind of lossless data transfer
from our internal structure the open
digital specimen to the dar core data
package which is kind of the um
transportation model um that we that we
use so that we don't lose any
information in that transformation to
the dark data package.
So the implementation um we uh implement
about 23 schemas and we were able to map
almost all of our opends terms in our
acceptance environment. Uh you can now
download any data set that we have both
as a DAR archive and as a DMO data
package. So you can actually view those
two and see what the what the
differences are. And um I think the
biggest data set we that we have now as
a daring core data package is about
750,000 records uh in total.
Uh and when when of course the daring
core data package in conceptual model
goes through u the ratification process
we'll we'll also move this to uh to our
production environment.
This is kind of the the overview. um
you'll see that really material media is
at the center of our OpenDS model and
and of course of our um D core data
package implementation
um and I've kind of shortened it that
the the A's are the agent as stands for
um assertions and ID for the identifier
class
um and yeah not all of our specimen will
have all this information but the
implementation is Yeah.
So what are the lessons that we have
learned from this uh implementation?
Well, the interoperability is is is
good. We we don't lose a lot of data in
the transformation. Um we do need to do
some triggery uh in the sense that yeah,
we we have this document approach. Um
and a lot of the relationships that we
have are actually implicit in it because
they're nested into in this in this
bigger object. we don't need an specific
identifiers for them. Um, so what we did
need to do was create a lot of
identifiers which we do through an MD
MD5 hash of the object and then uh we
needed to duplicate all the information
where uh where we use temporary tables.
So we we hash those and and use those uh
hashes as primary identifiers for the
object put it in database tables and
then dump those to uh to CSV files so
that we get the the data package
structure that we would we want
moving forward. I first want to take a
moment to congratulate the whole DL
conceptual model team. Um so John and
Tim and everybody involved in in in
getting this done. It's a monumental
effort. Um, and and please applaud them
for it. Um, and I'm hoping um that you
would be willing to participate in the
public review. It's it's essential to
now get get review back from from from
the general audience so we can further
improve it. Um and as OpenDS after
ratification process, we will move this
uh and probably move move the next
iterations of OpenDS further um closer
to the conceptual model and further
align classes and terms where they uh if
they aren't already. And we're looking
forward to further collaboration on
controlled vocabularies.
And this was uh my presentation. Thank
you for your attention.
Thank you very much for that Sam. As far
as I know, Sam is online and able to
answer questions in the chat for people
who are online but unable to answer
questions to everybody here uh in person
in Bogotaa. Uh if anybody has any
questions, I believe Walter, you said
you're allowed you're allowed, forgive
me, you're that's horrible. you're able
to answer um a question or two if
anybody has one um about
Sam's presentation.
No silence. Okay, then we will move on
and shift directions ever so slightly.
Uh our next speaker I'd like to invite
to the stage, Feder Federico Mendes is
here to talk to you a little bit about
the implementation status of the Darwin
core data package within JBIFF.
Okay. Hello everybody. My name is Ric
Mendes. I work for the JIF secretariat
in Copenhagen, Denmark. And I'm going to
give you a presentation about the
implementation status of Darwin core
data package at JIVF. The implementation
plan has defined the four main areas of
implementation. The first one is related
with data standards promotion and
support. That work has been presented by
by others here. The second one is is is
related with data publishing and and is
basically how the existing data
publishing workflows needs to be adapted
to support that core data package. The
third one it relates with once a data
set that has been shared as a as a as a
D call data package how that how that
data set should be should be presented
represented in the in the in the GI
platform in the GIF APIs and also in the
in the GI data portal and the and the
last one the data services that's the
that's the more long-term vision it is
and it's about what is about the design
and implementation of the data services
of the data that has been shared through
to through to through to through to
through data sets as sting core data
packages. Okay.
But based on those four areas of
implementation, we have defined for the
for the coming year three milestones. Uh
the first one is related with the data
publishing ledger and it's about how the
existing
publishing tools the a uh the IP and the
entity should be adapted to to to
support the tin core data packages. The
the second one is once we have a a data
set that has been published how what
will be the the minimum implementation
with the that to to show that data that
data set in the in the in the in the J
portal that work is going to be done in
the in the new uh J website. So so and
the and that should be available before
the end of the year. And the last one
that's the that's the long-term vision
of how to implement the integrated data
services of of of data that has been
published to data packages.
Uh for the milestone uh for the fifth
milestone so we have the the point one
and two are related with the schemas and
with the standards that's the work that
has been presented already. The third
one is about the implementational the
provisional implementational support in
both the IP and the MDT. my colleague
Mika he's going to do a presentation
about the current implementation in the
IP and and and also what are the future
plans for the IP for for TIN core data
packages there's already as as John
mentioned there's already a provisional
implementation in in in in the in the
MDT and I'm going to show a couple of
slides about that and then uh we will
also we like to implement data
validation tools in in mapping tools not
only in the context of those tools but
also as a data services that a user can
access in the GB portal to validate the
D core data packages that have been
assembled out of the context of those
tools.
Erh milestone two er we we would like to
mature the technical and and user
documentation and that's that's the work
that that has been also presented that's
can can be can you say that is is half
done so so far we would like to improve
the user experience for for for for for
mapping for mapping data in the IP mik
also going to present some some of the
ideas around that in the face m we're
only we're only doing the provisional
support but the second when we're going
to mature the implementation of the
mapping data in the in the IP. Uh we
would like also to to initiate a
versioning strategy for progressive
improvements. We we are totally aware
that this is just after the public
review is the first and draft
implementation of the standard. So we
have to anticipate how are we going to
accommodate the changes in the future.
Uh point four uh we would like to
implement the services and tools for
comparation between both DA core
archives into Darwin core data packages
and in in in in cases when it's also
possible how to convert from from data
packages into DR archive and that will
enable the different injection pipelines
in to to use in both to use that data in
both ways and then uh the final one
needs to is to improve the the data set
representation in the in the in the GB
portal.
And at the at the at the at the end of
the presentation, I'm going to give a an
example of of the progress that we have
done around that
for the mastering tree that's the work
for the future. We haven't defined a
specific tasks. Uh we know that we have
some some key challenges and those key
challenges that basically follow some of
the big questions. Tim Rosson mentioned
some of some of those in in this
milestone. We we we would like to tackle
questions like what are going to be the
new data services to do do we need one
multiple data portals given that we're
going to start receiving
data set with very different nature and
very different nature of data set to to
the data set that we have seen so far
and then in this master we'd like to
focus in the design of implementation of
multiple APIs and also in data services
So
what we have the done so far in this
example I'm showing here this is the
metabarcoding data toolkit uh in in the
metaboding toolkit a user can upload a
set of data files then can provide some
can provide some basic mapping from from
those data files into tar core terms and
at the end as a result can export the
result as a tarore archive or as a
dancing core data package that's the
provisional implementation that we have
so far in this case I'm skipping all the
registration steps in the middle but uh
but the daring corart data package is
been registered in the in the in the in
the in the in the jur in the jur
platform and then we can see here that
we are showing a basic let's say
graphical representation of how the data
set is organized in terms of of of
tables the the fields inside the tables
the relationships between the tables and
that's basically a graphical view of the
data package descriptor of the of that
specific data package. I just want to
emphasize that this is working in
progress. This is still in the developer
in developing environment and the and
the in the future work is to make this
available for the for the public.
And uh if I if I was in the in the demo
side, I can scroll down and I can
actually see some of the data that are
behind of those of those data resources.
So in this case for example uh you can
see the the the it's a basic exploration
of the of the event table of that data
package and and some of the other
tables. This is just to give the user
some kind of very generic perspective an
overview what data is behind a a data
package. What is the the future work for
this? So we would like to implement a a
download format that's a tore data
package. uh we would like to make this
work available also in the in the in the
demo site in the test site in cases when
the coordinates are are provided in in
any of those tables we would like to
provide a map view of those of those uh
of that data. We would also like to
provide some basic matrix in metrics in
the sense of how many records are behind
an specific table and what are the the
specific columns, how many records are
in a in a column, how how a column is
being populated for example. And then we
would like to also to integrate this
with the validation tools that that that
can pro provide some kind of report
about the validation status. Okay. And
we would also like to provide some kind
of basic API that that that that
supports the this data navigation key.
Sorry.
Uh just to mention a couple of things at
the end. We have been working on two
libraries. One is a is a basic Java
library that allows to to validate and
to and to and to read the data packages.
That's an extension that we've been work
working. And also uh we have imple
implemented a a library that allows to
read the data package in importing
multiple data stores. At this moment we
support the elastic search post and
clear house that way. Yep. Sorry. Yep.
So that's it.
Thank you.
Thank you very much, Federico. That was
very, very insightful into everything
that's going on here at Keith. And I
would like to welcome Male Podski Podski
up to the stage to continue this
conversation and tell us a little bit
about the uh the tool data tools that
are being developed and explored.
Good afternoon everyone. Uh my name is
Mikail and I'm uh lead developer for IP
or integrated publishing toolkit in
JBIF. IP was uh mentioned multiple times
today and it's a basically a publishing
tool. It's a formatting and sharing tool
for to GB and OBS.
So uh and today I'm going to talk about
uh
uh implementing Darian core data package
in AP and what challenges we had on the
way and ideas we had for it. So let's
get started.
So what are the ch what are the
challenges we have currently? So the
first is uh it's a new model which can
be
uh overwhelming for users because it's a
new model. It's huge. There is a lot of
tables in it and what are those tables
and what fields it is. So it's it's
complicated.
The second one is uh uh it's relational
model. So there will be a lot of
identifiers and connection between those
tables and there's a lot of join tables.
Uh so that's the second thing.
Uh yeah and uh
yeah and the third I already mentioned
that's uh identifiers and uh how we
maintain those identifiers and yeah
so the current view of IPs uh so-al
display all the tables so you you can
see what how it would look like if we
put all 70 plus tables in the dropdown.
So it obviously doesn't scale this
approach.
So we have to find uh UI solution to
solve this issue.
Uh one of the ideas to solve this thing
is uh introduce new concept of a profile
or template which would be a subset of
the model with uh
uh some tables and fields their fields
with the comprehensive description of it
and some keywords for search. They can
be public or local. they can be
downloadable online or not
or yeah um you can create resources from
these templates you can edit those
templates and yeah basically that's the
idea so here's the example for for
example for pentological data set which
is a madeup example it's it's not real
data data set profile so just just the
idea it can be many many profiles
Um sorry. So for implementing profiles
and managing them in the AP we would
need um
a tool within the AP to
uh to manage those profiles to edit them
to add add fields to add tables and save
them upload them download them and
basically the whole management
structure.
So next one. All right. So we're done
with profiles. The next thing it's uh
navigating the model. Either we mapping
just data or editing profile or
whatever. We would need to navigate
model somehow. And as we we seen already
multiple times, it's a big model. So we
would need some kind of help with that.
So uh we have some ideas with that that
can be categories for categorize some of
the tables to for uh simplified search.
Uh it can be uh improved drop-own list
which we already have in uh Daring or uh
test a um and it can be advanced search
engine for these tables terms or
everything. So this is about search how
we would like to see search for this uh
for diving core data package. So it if
we put for example
collector so uh it would look through
all the fields examples and descriptions
and we'll provide the comprehensive uh
view of all the matching things.
Uh all right let's go next. So for
another uh visualize the model. So
currently we have on the
uh resource which we have the old list
of all map tables and how the map from
sources to those tables but it probably
would be a good idea to have some kind
of uh schematic visualization which is
to the left with all connections that
would be useful. I think that's already
implemented in the MDT.
And uh the last idea was mentioned
multiple times during previous
presentation. It's a uh complexity of
managing identifiers. So there could be
many ideas but uh we were thinking about
something that we called splitting
tools. So let's say we have a example
source data with
event ID and date and a collector and we
would like to split that into three
tables in Daring data package and every
single table has its own identifier and
it would be good to have some kind of
tool that would
uh generate this ID and will just uh
help users with uh this and so it can be
just data without all those additional
identifiers.
Um,
thank you from so much for your
attention. That's it.
>> We have time for a question if anyone
a
>> Thank you. Thank you so much for your
presentation. My question is for Fed. Um
I'm wondering the milestones are they
going to be implemented sequentially?
The reason I asked is because it's
important for the data consumer to know
um what is the meaningful search uh for
them in order to develop products and
this information should go into how to
guide to publish the data. So yeah it
would be nice and you could please
address that. Thank you.
>> That that that's a that's a very good
question. I didn't address that in the
in the in the presentation, but no, the
the answer is not that sequential
milestones, especially the milestone one
and milestone two. So, so, so the
intention is that we we the user can
start publishing the D core data
packages as soon as possible and we need
to to provide some kind of mechanism to
to to to to view that those data sets
and that also has to be in company with
with with with with better documentation
and technical documentation that core
data packages. So, so no that was I
omitted that in the presentation but
this especially the two first ones are
are not sequential milestones. The third
one is a is a bit of the work for the
future. Yeah.
>> Okay, we're going to need to move on to
the the next presentation. Thank you
very much. Thank you very much,
Federico.
So, we've come a long way in 70 minutes
from an excellent introduction and
overview of what the Darwin Core data
package is to getting a better
understanding of how it will relate to
other standards, the Disco's OpenDS and
ABCD understand getting an idea of where
we're at here at JBIFF in thinking about
how we would implement the data package.
One thing we didn't do was explain what
a data package is. Don't worry, John has
a session on Friday doing just that,
introducing you to data packages. So for
those of you who like me coming into
this didn't actually know what a data
package is, think I have a basic
understanding now. Attend John's session
on Friday. Now we will move on to our
last presentation for the day and this
is a present a virtual presentation from
Steve Basco and it's bringing you to the
crux of the issue. the reason why we're
here introducing you to Darwin Core data
package introducing you to the fact that
this is under review through Tadwig and
Steve will help you for those of you who
are not familiar with the review process
he will introduce you to that and help
guide you through that uh so that you
can leave here today and go rush out and
test the Darcore data package with your
own data.
I'm Steve Baskoff, the convenor of the
Darwin Core Maintenance Group. In that
role, I'm responsible for overseeing the
management of the public review of the
Darwin Core data packages proposal.
Some of you may have participated in
past reviews of proposed changes to
Darwin Core vocabularies.
For those who haven't, I will briefly
summarize the general change process,
then explain how the process for this
review differs from past reviews.
The overall process of making changes to
a Tadwig vocabulary is governed by the
vocabulary maintenance specification and
is summarized in this diagram.
Any person or group may propose changes
or additions.
Periodically, the maintenance group
responsible for the vocabulary will
review proposals in light of three
criteria.
Demand by the community, efficacy to
meet an identified need, and whether the
change will maintain stability of
existing implementations.
Proposed changes meeting these criteria
are approved by the maintenance group to
undergo a 30-day public comment period
during which consensus about the
proposal is sought. If consensus is
achieved, the executive committee makes
sure that the procedures have been
followed properly and ratifies the
change.
More complicated changes that go beyond
the basic bag of terms layer of the
vocabulary are known as vocabulary
enhancements.
Because they're more complicated, it's
required that user feedback documents be
submitted with the proposal to make it
clear that the package of changes are
needed and will work as described.
In the case of the Dolan core data
packages proposal, there are two
documents that describe structure on top
of the basic term layer. The conceptual
model document describes in human terms
the relationships among classes in
Darwin core. The data package guide
specifies a mechanism based on
frictionless data packages for
documenting the fields in data tables
and how those tables are related to each
other.
A number of terms need to be added or
modified to make it possible to impose
this structure.
In the same way that Darwin core
archives implement the requirements of
the text guide, Darwin core data
packages will implement the requirements
of the data packages guide.
However, these implementation details
are outside of the standard and aren't
part of the review.
To view these documents and the proposed
term changes, there are links from a
landing page at the URL shown at the
bottom of this slide. This landing page
is also linked from the news item
announcing the public review on the
TAWIG website at tadwig.org.
You can jump directly to the document
links using the sidebar index.
The proposed term changes are also
accessible via a link in the sidebar
index. Because of the large number of
proposed changes, I find it easiest to
review the changes grouped by class
using the issue summary linked circled
here.
After carefully reviewing the proposal
package and the user feedback and
implementation experience report, the
dollar core maintenance group approved
moving the proposal to public comment in
September.
The public review is ongoing until at
least December 16th. This period of
review is 90 days rather than the normal
30 days due to the complexity of the
proposal.
If you want to participate in the review
of the two documents, you can follow the
links in the participating in the review
section of the landing page. This will
lead you to the appropriate place in the
GitHub issue tracker for the Darwin Core
repository.
From there, you can create or comment on
issues related to the documents.
To comment on the proposed term changes,
navigate to the proposal issue in the
tracker for the relevant term. As I
mentioned earlier, an easy way to do
this is via the issues summary link,
which will lead you to summary issues
for each class. From these summary
issues, you can find the appropriate
subisssue for each term where it is
possible to add your comment in the
tracker.
In all cases, comments are made on an
appropriate issues page in the tracker.
If you have difficulty using the GitHub
issue tracker system, you can also
directly email your comments to me and
I'll post them on your behalf.
As issues arise, members of the public
and the submission team will have
dialogue through the comments. The
maintenance group will try to resolve
the issues through modifying the
particular proposal in a way that
obtains consensus.
The dollar core maintenance group
encourages anyone who is interested to
participate in the review. Please keep
in mind that some available materials
show how the changes will be
implemented. These implementation
details happen outside of the standard
and are therefore not subject to the
review which is focused only on the two
proposed documents and the term changes
related to them.
Also keep in mind that the conceptual
model and data packages guide will be
primarily used by application
developers. So if you're an enduser,
don't feel bad if you don't have
comments to offer on those documents.
There will be additional opportunities
for user feedback as implementations
based on the new documents are
developed.
Thanks for your time and I'm happy to
answer any questions here or via email.
So this concludes the presentations that
we have scheduled for today. We have
about 15 minutes left for questions
which uh considering the number of hands
I've seen pop up occasionally between
presentations I fear may not be enough.
So, if we do not get to your question
today, I would like to remind you that
we do have unconference sessions at
which you could potentially
recommend or suggest additional
conversations be continued. On that
note, uh why don't we start with
question Nikki? Oh, Nikki had her hand
up. We'll start with Nikki and then
we'll move on.
Hey, get them in my head. I can't ask
Steve questions. Is that right?
I can't ask Steve questions.
You can ask Steve.
Okay. Um, I wondered what the coverage
of people is that submit comments to the
review periods. Like, do we know that we
get adequate commenting?
>> That's a super good question. as a big
worry uh especially with this one
because it's so complex in practice
during Darwin core reviews
uh the simpler ones we get plenty of
interaction we have some conversations
that go on and on and on because they're
complex topics and as a result sometimes
not even consensus is achieved and when
consensus is not achieved the proposal
is not included. Here we have an even
more complex situation where often there
are interdependencies
like if you if we couldn't get consensus
on one thing it the whole a whole
cascade of breakdowns could occur. In
answer directly to your question, I fear
that our community isn't sufficiently
educated on what all this means to be
able to make meaningful comments for a
lot of it. However,
it's being addressed in exactly the same
way as all Darwin core reviews have ever
been done, which is the mechanism that
Steve showed and at the level of
most of our community. It's looking at
the terms that are being proposed. Are
are the terms necessary? Is there a
better way to do it? Are they
sufficiently well described? Is anything
ambiguous? that sort of thing. And in
that respect, the hope with those issue
summaries was that you as an vested
interested person could identify the
parts of it that matter to you and go
directly there and forget the rest of
it. So that was a hope by doing a new
kind of organization of issues that
we've never done before. I can't predict
how many of you might participate.
So far there's been fair participation
but on some topics that are really
pretty heavy you know no conceptual
semantic philosophical religious
so I don't know exactly how to answer
the core question but that's that's the
panorama
>> I I think um Erica Criminal has uh
volunteered um hope I'm not speaking out
of turn to in to um you know host some
Darwin core um what did you call them
hours Darwin core hours to um deal with
the discussion of all of this and help
people continue to get further educated
about it. Um so I I don't know that
those have been scheduled yet but I
think they will be uh fairly soon.
Are there any questions? No. Okay.
>> Sorry. I I also have a question which
which refers to the review process. If
you take the time and review the model
or part of the model and you you come to
the conclusion that you agree with what
has been proposed, is there a way to
state this? Because I think it's it's
also an important information if people
agree with with the model or parts of
the model.
>> It's a very good point. Uh this came up
in a previous review where basically
we're assessing Nikki's question that
okay the people who aren't saying
anything who are there are there people
out there who see this? Yes. So the only
built-in mechanism without just flooding
the issue with more comments is to use
the the little icons for thumbs up and
so on. So it's very useful to have that
kind of feedback. No. And and in fact
when somebody well known makes a comment
with a thumbs up some of their friends
like okay now I feel better and they go
put their thumbs up that helps us
>> helps us to know what matters to people
as well. So good point good question.
>> Thanks. Uh my question is to Misha who's
developing the IP.
So actually maybe it's between question
and a suggestion. So um I know that the
dharmic core data package has been
tested with different uh study cases use
cases uh by different thematic
communities. So do you think that you
can reach out to thematic communities to
propose? I liked very much the idea of
data state profile. So maybe they could
help or you can even have a call from
differentiatic communities to propose
and to endorse some data set profiles.
Yeah, that's it.
The idea of profiles that uh users uh
make their own profile. So we just
implement the concept of profile and the
rest is up to community. So they decide
what they need. We don't manage those
profiles.
The idea behind the user guide which
will be I think it's development has
started but will take some time to put
together is to do exactly what you're
talking about is to think about you know
if you have a specific data types or
specific uses or purposes here's the
place to start here's the the tenative
framework you might have to tweak it a
little bit for your specific use case
but this is kind of the domain specific
or data specific idea. Pass it to Tim.
>> Thank you. Um I'll introduce myself
again in case anyone joined in the
second section. I'm Tim Robertson um
deputy director and head of informatics
at JBIF. I I'd like to follow up on on
the profile comment and it's been very
interesting to John and I because when
we went through the data modeling work
over the last few years, we built a
conceptual model and then we had this
idea of publishing models for different
communities and we started going down
that road where we had the cold DP for
the checklists. We had Camtra DP for
camera trap specific projects and we
were starting to think about communitysp
specific publishing models and we got
some quite strong feedback suggesting
please don't do that because you have
the potential to fragment our community
and we were we were encouraged to try
and bring it back together into a single
publishing model. So this has been a
really interesting experience for John
and I that as we did that what we found
this things got more complicated again
and people are now looking at it and
they're saying wow this is overwhelming.
We've got some people saying, "Wow, this
is really exciting. I can see my data
fits in there." And lots of other
people, many with operational
experience, are going, "Wow, are we
really going to be able to do that?" So,
what's coming out is the idea again of
profiles, simplified publishing models.
And it could well be that maybe we do
land in that place with simplified
profiles. But we know that you can
integrate those data together in a
larger conceptual model should you need
to. Now I would like to comment on one
other operational thing. Um meta
barcoding data is exploding in the GPIF
community and we are seeing lots and
lots of uh data sets and activities
there and
we have Darwin core archives and we have
extensions. We've got the DNA extension
for Darwin core archives. We are now
seeing Darwin core archives with around
about 27 million detections of organisms
using metabarcoding Edna techniques. And
these archives are half a terabyte of
data. And the reason they're half a
terabyte is because of that star schema.
You've got the environmental assertions
that are, you know, the what was uh
measured while you were making your
samples. You've got the DNA analysis
measurements and and metadata
um which is both repeated for every
occurrence and you've got massive
massive repetition. So as a data
publishing model for metabarcoding, it
ain't going to work. So the Darbon core
data package um has been implemented in
the GBIFF metabarcoding data toolkit.
The same input data in some cases can
drop a thousand times in size because of
that repetition. So not 10 times bigger,
not a 100 times but three orders of
magnitude difference by these two
formats. So just for operational reasons
as we move into meta barcoding data we
will need to implement something like
this. So it could well be and I'm I'm
not trying to contradict Fede in any
way. Actually while I have the mic I'd
like to congratulate Federico on his uh
his recent promotions being head of
engineering at JVIF. leads all of our
engineering aspects. But it could well
be that we at JBIF will need to
implement part of this to support the
metabarcoding community even if we don't
support everything all in one go. So
where where we are at this stage is we
feel like we've taken this modeling work
to a good point that we can bring to the
community. And that's the great thing
about Tadwig and and this world. We can
have open discussion about this and we
can put a proposal up and we can
consider it and we can reflect on the
feedback and that's where we are right
now is rather than this just being a
JVIF activity. We now think this is
moving towards a standards direction. So
we bring it to Tadwick and we ask you to
give us feedback and we will reflect and
revise and react to that and and that's
where we are in this process. So thank
you.
Thank you, Tim. And that's the perfect
segue back to our first question and
with to which Steve Basco has provided a
response in in the the chat as well. And
so he specifically said that the number
of comments depend on the topic. And so
there have been significant discussion
on some issues and no discussion on
other.
And we have approximately 5 minutes left
in the session. Time for one, possibly
two questions depending on how dense the
question is.
Thanks.
I'm curious to hear about how
accommodating the Darwin core data
package is to trait measurements. My my
understanding is that measurements
uh you know assertions can be made on um
materials or occurrences. Um but maybe
specifically is the data package
accommodating of nested trait
measurements. You know for example you
might have a plant specimen with leaf
measurements but leaves are grouped by
branch and you have multiple branches
for specimens that per specimen etc.
Okay. Um there is no
recursive relationship on assertions at
the at this time. It was considered but
we didn't have a strong use case for it.
It can still be done but I would call it
a cluge and that is adding yet another
assertion talking about the previous
assertion. It's not connected the right
way and so it's not clearly obvious. So
the other other existing examples of how
this might be used were not nearly as
problematic. For example, statistics
about something. A measurement that was
a mean and its standard deviation.
There's not really any problem to
connect the two to a material sample.
Uh and but you're relying on the control
vocabulary about the assertion type to
know that they're related to each other.
So if we have strong need to make these
kinds of relationships that are strong
then it's a simple change we add another
term which is the related to assertion
ID that can allow that recursive
recursiveness.
So have a good use case bring it.
So I have a question that might bridge
that question and some of the review
questions which is it seems to me not
having been part of the review process
that these use cases have been great
ways of probing the model and finding
ways it needs to be improved.
Is there a forum in which maybe as a
verbal thing, as a meeting kind of
thing, we can bring together some people
who have weird use cases and
sophisticated people who really know the
proposed model who could talk through,
oh yeah, yeah, that's easy to take care
of. Here's how we would do it. Or, oh
crap, I'm not sure. We'll have to think
about that without us having to deeply
understand all the aspects of the model
to be able to answer it ourselves
because we probably can't do it
correctly.
>> If I'm allowed to say what I want
>> to say what I want.
>> Yeah. Um, we've been basically doing
what you just said now for over a year
and the plan is to continue that. And
the hope would be that now we can
produce more experts that can answer
such questions instead of just me. But
the plan would be that at least for the
next year I'm available to help with
exactly that.
Nikki actually Oh,
>> two minutes left. Yeah. Okay.
Lynn and then Nikki and then I think we
are out of time for questions for today.
>> Okay, just a short question. So I was
wondering um what to do with project
level uh metadata. So I'm familiar with
the Darwin core archives that's the EML.
Um but uh when I try to map the project
level metadata I could also use the
highest events. So I'm not sure what is
the role of EML in the DRA core data
package. Where do you map project level
data? That's my question.
>> Yeah,
>> it's on. Now it's on. Um, yeah, projects
are interesting. We had a preliminary
investigation into projects as a class
and
uh left it without implementation
because we didn't have the use case that
we needed to solve yet. We knew it was
important. GBF already sees the demand
for this but we don't have the project
class implemented. All we have at the
moment is as you said metadata in EML or
in the provenance class to say project
name. So yes, project titles and project
ids but that's not the metadata. You can
list them but not what you're talking
about. So yes, we can develop a project
class. Happy to do so.
>> Okay. And last question.
I I really liked what you said about um
developing more experts.
So, how do you plan to go about that?
>> That's a very good question. Um we start
by sharing where we are and that's what
we're doing in this conference. We're
bringing it to the correct body tadwick
to have this discussion. Um I think we
have taken it as far as we could um with
the work that we did at JIB. Um so
that's that's why we bring this this
work forward. So
we we held a um training event for the
GBIFF node managers and the GBIFF node
man and and that's an internal meeting.
So I'm actually going to correct
something that John said earlier where
the the training that JVIF had was
really an internal um socializing this
work across the JVIF node management
community so that they can start to
understand it and they they're daunted
as well. You know this is daunting
because we are going back to expert
models that um were Anton presented and
we're trying to sort of train people up
on database modeling which is which is
hard for for for many people. So we we
started trying to to build that capacity
and train people across the JVIF
community and then they hopefully will
be able to sort of proliferate that out
around their communities. We're bringing
it to Tadwig um to to ask uh the Tadwick
community to look and you know
progressively expand on this. Um
what we've talked about and what's come
up in the JVIF discussions is we need to
keep our community together. um this
can't just be an informatics, you know,
we want to go there quickly and just
lose everyone. That's not going to work.
So, we are, you know, we we will
probably make mistakes in this process.
Um but we're trying to to put it out as
as something for discussion um so that
we can we can reflect and feedback on
that. Um but yeah, we would welcome
ideas and suggestions on on how we can
improve this. Thank you. Thanks.
would.
>> So following up on that and as Tim said
during the global nodes training just
this last week, we did do a training
session on the DAR core data package and
all of the materials are freely
available on the website. I have a QR
code. Awkward. I didn't have a chance to
put it up anywhere. So, you're welcome
to come up afterwards and scan my phone
so you can go find it yourself on your
own phone. But the training materials
are opened. They're free. They're there
for people to use and and and learn a
little bit more about the uh about the
Darn Core data package themselves. And
on that, we are out of time. I want to
say a big thank you to all of our
speakers. You did fantastic. We learned
a whole lot from you. I hope people
follow up with you through the rest of
the conference and keep you very busy.
Thank you to our audience. You've been
awesome. Fantastic questions. Lots of
stuff for us to think about. And I hope
you have a wonderful evening. Thanks.
You got
the cowboy. I can't
[Music]
even know why.
connect.
[Music]
reasonable.
I can
United.
[Music]
Sorry.
black.
All we need is You can't